Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף י"ד,
Daf Yud Daled, and we pick up with the משנה Mishnah at
the bottom of י"ג, Yud Gimmel,
and we turn from the prohibition of doing business, whether it's on
the holiday or the market day, and the consequences of doing business,
the fine that they would apply, that they would destroy the stuff
that you got, well at least certainly on the market day, not
clear if that was true about the holiday as well,
and the issues about deriving benefit, giving benefit, and now we really
switch gears to a separate concern, which is selling them things throughout
the year that they might wind up using in their idolatrous
practice. And for some that was also part of the concern about
doing business before their holidays, whether they would use the animals to
sacrifice, you might remember that that was a way the גמרא Gemara
framed the issue. But anyway, but here it's much more general and
it's much more explicit that that's the concern. This also became very
relevant for the ראשונים, Rishonim, particularly the אשכנזי Ashkenazi ראשונים, Rishonim, who
actually one of the major areas they did business in was
Christian religious items, selling them directly even to the church. Okay, so
with that in mind, let's take a look at this משנה Mishnah
here at the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב'. Yud Gimmel Amud Bet.
So,
אלו דברים אסורים למכור לעובדי כוכבים, aylu devarim assurim limkor l'ovdei kochavim,
the following things are prohibited to sell to an idolater:
אצטרובלין, itzrublin, and we'll see what that means in the גמרא, Gemara,
it always makes me think of like a strobe lighting or something,
anyway אצטרובלין itzrublin but that's not what it is, it's some type
of a plant or whatever, some types of things that they would
use to decorate
in front of their idol, which again the also question is what
type of איסור issur are they doing? It doesn't, it's not going
to seem like from the גמרא Gemara that they're using this as
a form of an offering as an act of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah per se, it's some type of a participation in their pagan
ritual but that doesn't mean it's an act of worship, right? Maybe
it's an act of adorning their
idol, for a Jew that wouldn't be עבודה זרה avodah zarah that
would be the death penalty, that might be a לאו, lav, right?
So anyway it's interesting also what type of thing are you indirectly
participating or are you
enabling?
Anyway at any time of the year,
at any time of the year, these are classic things that would
be used in this type of worship context.
Did they not have any other use?
Well we'll see about that, okay
but these are certainly likely primary use and whatever, and that's a
key question, so hold off on that but yes it's good that
you're asking that. בנות שוח, bnot shuach, another type of thing, the
גמרא Gemara will say that that's like a white
fig, ופטוטרות, uptotrot, their stems, okay the גמרא Gemara will say that
that means that you can't sell these things with their stems attached
because that would let them string them up by their stems so
they would be nicer to get them separately
presumably. ולבונה ulevonah and frankincense, okay that's actually an act of like
a type of worship burning frankincense. תרנגול הלבן tarnegol halvavan and a
white chicken which presumably would also be used as an actual act
of something that would be brought as an offering presumably. Red what?
White chickens you know for a fact?
Yeah, I mean I remember this, this was back when I was
in Columbia when I took a course in demonology, magic, and miracles,
and our same מחלוקת machloket about כפרות, kaparot, right, they had that
exact, exact מחלוקת machloket for an eclipse like what do you do
when
there's
an eclipse you
anyway
yeah so they would use it in
some type of ritual these rituals white chicken. Yeah, I mean and
it was a question like let's say you're a pregnant woman what
kind you take?
There you go. Okay but the good interesting question again is, is
it some type of a ritual or is it some type of
an actual offering like is it brought as a sacrifice? So that's
an interesting question what exactly are they doing with it that makes
them technically transgressing the בני נח Bnei Noach prohibition of עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, right, if they do pagan rituals are they transgressing the
בני נח Bnei Noach prohibition of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? So I
think it's an interesting question what exactly they're doing with it, okay.
ורבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, now רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would
say מותר למכור לו תרנגול לבן בין התרנגולים, mutar limkor lo tarnegol
lavan bein haternegolim, if you don't know that they're specifically focused on
that maybe they just want to have some chicken soup at home
so that's okay, so how do you know, well if they specifically
ask or select the white chicken that's a problem but if they
buy a crate full of chickens then there's a white one you
don't have to take it out.
ובזמן
שהוא בפני עצמו קוטע את אצבעו ומוכרו
לו,
ubizman shehu bifnei atzmo koteia et etzbao u-mochro
lo,
but if you're selling him just the white chicken itself so cut
off the finger because בני נח Bnei Noach don't offer up sacrifices
that are missing a limb presumably or and pagans don't also. Okay
and then you can sell it to him לפי שאין מקריבין חסר
לעבודת כוכבים, lefi she'ein makrivin chaser l'avodat kochavim, they don't offer it
up with a missing limb to their pagan God. Again that's now
certainly by the chicken case it's a concern about directly actually offering
it up as a sacrifice. Mentioning eclipses by the way I should
mention to everybody my son told me that apparently Wednesday morning... It's
going to be this
blood
red moon or something, just to be aware 6:00 a.m. Anyway ושאר
כל הדברים v'shar kol had'varim just an opportunity to see מעשה השם.
ma'aseh Hashem. ושאר כל הדברים סתמן מותר v'shar kol had'varim staman mutar
per our משנה. mishnah. Other things, if they're just buying them generically,
it's fine. But if they say explicit, "Oh, it's my holiday, can
you sell me a palm branch and a..." No, that's a different
holiday. That would be a good joke. Not a... what do they
have... a citron? Anyway, if they say specifically, like you know, it's
so funny, you're out there on the street buying אתרוגים ולולבים etrogim
v'lulavim and these non-Jews are walking by and they're trying to figure
out what's so special about these things. So anyway, so if they
come by and they make it clear that they want this for
some type of a pagan ritual, you know, and how clear do
they have to be, that makes it forbidden. Okay. רבי מאיר אומר
Rebbi Meir omer אף דקל טב וחצב af dekel tav v'chatzav אסור
asur ונקלס v'niklas אסור למכור לעובדי כוכבים. asur limkor l'ovdei kochavim. You
even can't sell them, literally this means some a good palm tree
and חצב chatzav some type of a grass it sounds like, and
some other things you can't sell. Anyway we'll have to figure out
what all these words mean. Okay, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Top of
14a. מאי אצטרובלין? mai itztroblin? תורניסא. turnisa. It's תורניסא. turnisa. What רש"י
Rashi says means a cedar tree, although תוספות Tosafot says it actually
means some type of a mineral.
ורמינהו urminhu I'll ask you on this: הוסיפו עליהן אלכסין
ואיצטרובלין
מכססין ובנות שוח. hosifu aleihen alachsin v'itztroblin machsasin uvnot shuach. They added
to the things to which שמיטה shmita would apply, these four things:
אלכסין alachsin I have no idea, אצטרובלין itztroblin is what we're talking
about, מכססין machsasin I also don't know, and בנות שוח bnot shuach
which we'll see which is also mentioned in our משנה mishnah which
were these types of white figs. So why these were not initially
included in שמיטה, shmita, why you can tell me what they mean
if they have... do they have a translation or not? It's a
cedar tree, the friggin' fruit...
Yeah, and one I've never heard of called an ilex, it says.
Okay, now we know. Okay, let's move
on. Okay, anyway. So the reason that these were added to שמיטה,
shmita, why weren't they initially on the list of שמיטה? shmita? It
could be that they were not considered to be like, you know,
a
things that תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion why they might not
have exactly been on the list. Some of them might be because
it was not clear exactly which year they grew, they grew over
a period of years and maybe technically they didn't exactly fall out
during a שמיטה shmita year. Another possible explanation is that they were
considered to be like something that were not really edible. Okay, not
exactly clear why they were not initially on the list. But anyway,
ואי סלקא דעתך אצטרובלין תורניסא, v'i salka datchach itztroblin turnisa,
now if you think אצטרובלין itztroblin is this תורניסא, turnisa, which let's
go with תוספות's Tosafot's explanation, it's some type of a mineral. So
תורניסא מי איתא בשביעית? turnisa mi ita b'shvi'it? You don't have שמיטה
shmita applying to a mineral. שמיטה shmita only applies to something that
grows. דתניא d'tanya we taught in a ברייתא: braita: זה הכלל כל
שיש לו עיקר יש לו שביעית. zeh haklal kol sheyesh lo ikar
yesh lo shvi'it.
If something basically, you know, is has roots in the ground and
grows from the ground it has שמיטה. shmita. וכל שאין לו עיקר
אין לו שביעית. v'chol she'ein lo ikar ein lo shvi'it. If it
doesn't it doesn't. And for תוספות Tosafot that means if something like
this it's a mineral, does not have שמיטה shmita applying to it.
So therefore clearly it is not a mineral if it's in the
list of things that שמיטה shmita applies. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אלא אמר רב ספרא פירי דארזא. ela amar Rav Safra peirei d'arza.
Fine, it is fruit from a cedar tree, some type of a
thing, which again maybe was a question of whether שמיטה shmita applied
because תוספות Tosafot says either because of let's say wasn't initial... wasn't
really questionable whether it was edible or not, but in the end
they decided שמיטה shmita did apply. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי
אלעזר פירי דארזא. v'chen ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Eleazar peirei d'arza.
This fruit of the of this cedar tree, some type of a
thing. רש"י Rashi says the fruit of cedar trees, רש"י Rashi says
גולנא, golna, if you look at
רש"י. Rashi. So not really an edible thing, but some type of
a thing again that they would use to bedeck the עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, and maybe for whatever reason they eventually included it in
the שמיטה shmita list. You have something to add about this... these
names?
Yeah, no, actually it's a very interesting note here, Steinsaltz about the
אצטרובלין. itztroblin. So he says that it... it can refer to a
variety of rounded objects, including the cones of a particular type of
tree,
oh pine cones,
yeah, which was, you know, he said very common for Asclepius, the
Greek god of medicine. They actually had these statues with him holding
the staff
with the pine cone on it. Oh, cool. That's pretty cool. Okay,
so pine cones, that makes sense also why it wasn't initially in
the שמיטה shmita list. Doesn't explain why it eventually was in the
שמיטה shmita list, pine cones are completely inedible. But you can certainly
understand like pine cones are big and you know, visible, whatever, they're
very nice also, symmetrical, right? So you could understand that they used
them in some type of a hanging ritual. Oh, that's a nice
explanation, pine cones. Okay, now בנות שוח. bnot shuach. What are בנות
שוח? bnot shuach? אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן תאני
חיורתא. amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan te'enei chivarta. White
figs. And again this was something that maybe weren't so edible. Long
תוספות. Tosafot. Whenever בנות שוח bnot shuach appears in the גמרא Gemara
there are these huge תוספותים. Tosafotim. Because some גמרות Gemarot make them
sound like they weren't particularly edible and didn't taste good and other
גמרות Gemarot make them sound like they were a delicacy. So תוספות
Tosafot tries to figure out: are there different types of בנות שוח?
bnot shuach? Anyway, so these were things that A, they were both
added later to the שמיטה shmita list, so maybe they weren't really
edible. But regardless and maybe that's also going back to Michael's question,
why you have to assume that they're being used for an עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. Because if they're not edible, why else does... do
people buy them? Maybe the prime reason people are buying them is
for these עבודה זרה avodah zarah things. And they were used presumably
to string in front of the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. How do
we know that? From the next line, because it says ופטטורות u'ptotrot
which are their... stems. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbah bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan בפטוטרותיהן שנו. biptutroteihen shanu.
We don't mean it's forbidden to buy stems, sell stems, stems, stems,
we mean that you can't sell them with their stems, and Rashi
says why not? So if you look at the first Rashi, first
narrow line,
בפטוטרותיהן שנו, biptutroteihen shanu, פטוטרות דמתניתין לאו מינהו בפני עצמו באפי נפשיה,
ptutrot dematnitin lav minhu bifnei atzmo be'apei nafshei, it's not a separate
type of a thing you used to sell them, אלא הכי קאמר
אין מוכרין להן כל אלו אצטרובלין ובנות שוח באוקציהן, ela hachi ka'amar
ein mochrin lahen kol eileu itztroblin ubenot shuach be'uktzeihen, don't sell them
with their stems, לפי שתולין אותם לפני עבודת כוכבים, lefi shetolin otam
bifnei avodat kochavim, ודרכם לעבדן בכך. vedarkam le'ovdan bekach. They would string
it before the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but then Rashi adds three
words to address the question I was raising. So what is it?
It's just a ritual? It's just beautifying an עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
Since when is beautifying an עבודה זרה avodah zarah the actual prohibition
of worshipping עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? So Rashi says, the keywords in
Rashi is ודרכם לעבדן בכך. vedarkam le'ovdan bekach. Yes, for that particular
עבודה זרה avodah zarah this was considered an act of worship, not
just a ritual, but an act of worship by stringing these things
in front of it. Okay, so that becomes this important question, right?
Is it that you can't sell them ritual objects or you can't
sell them objects that they use in an actual act of worship?
And Rashi is saying that in the end he's framing this as
a type of an act of worship they did with these things.
Yeah, and there's another הערה he'arah here. So the אלוכסין, alaxin, so,
you know, keeping with the pine cone thing, this would be acorns,
he says. Okay, and בנות שוח benot shuach oftentimes, yeah, we have
this oak thing. So anyway, all these things, you know, fertility rights,
like Dionysus and all this kind of.
Oh, interesting. Although that list of אלוכסין alaxin or whatever was for
שמיטה, shmitah, but בנות שוח benot shuach and the pine cones, that's
interesting, fertility rights. Okay.
Yeah, acorns, interesting.
לבונה, levonah, frankincense. Okay, that we could certainly understand as an act
as a ritual, not just ritual, something that was brought as an
object of worship to or an object to be offered, I should
say, an offering, לבונה. levonah. אמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי שמעון לקיש
לבונה זכה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Amar Rabbi Shimon Lakish levonah zakkah, pure
frankincense. תנא ומכולן מוכרין להן חבילה. Tana umikulan mochrin lahen chavilah.
But you can sell them in bulk. You can sell them in
a what's it called, a pallet? Is that what it's called, a
pallet, like a big thing when you, you know, anyway, you can
sell like a big bundle of them. You can sell it in
bulk because then you're just selling it to a wholesaler. He's not
actually going to use it, he's just going to retail it then,
or you're the wholesaler, you're going to sell it to a guy
who's going to then, but then the people who are going to
buy from him. Gemara's going to ask that question. Okay. So it
says, וכמה חבילה, vekamah chavilah, how big is a חבילה? chavilah? פירש
רבי יהודה בן בתירה אין חבילה פחות משלושה מנין, peireish Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira ein chavilah p-chus mishlosha manin, three מנין. manin. So that's
a very large size, I don't know exactly how much it is,
I don't know, we'll call it 20 pounds. I just made that
up. Okay. וחוש שמא אזיל ומזבין לאחרים כך? ve-hush shema azil umazvin
leachrin kach? Okay, but then he's going to go sell it, so
fine, you're not selling it to a guy who's going to use
it. You're selling it to a guy who's then going to retail
it or whatever, you know, distribute it, and then the people that
come and buy it from him are going to use it. So
the Gemara says, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, very important principle, one line
here, very important in the parameters of לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, אמר
אביי אלפני מפקדינן אלפני דלפני לא מפקדינן. Amar Abaye Alifnei mefaktinan Alifnei
delifnei lo mefaktinan. We are prohibited on the prohibition of לפני עיוור,
lifnei iver, do not put a stumbling block before the blind. We
are not prohibited on do not put a stumbling block before, like,
you know, do not do it one step removed. Do not put
a stumbling block in front of somebody that his stumbling block is
that he'll put a stumbling block before somebody else, you know. So
don't do it two steps removed. One step, yes, is that true
eventually what's going to do, but you do not directly participate in
the final person's sin, you're one degree removed, and therefore you do
not, you're not transgress. Now here's a little fun question that the
אחרונים acharonim ask. So the middle person here, there are two non-Jews
in the equation. I sold to a non-Jew, non-Jew sells to whatever.
And we're presumably non-Jews are not prohibited with לפני עיוור, lifnei iver,
right? A non-Jew is not prohibited in the שבע מצוות בני נח
sheva mitzvot bnei Noach to cause another non-Jew to sin or to,
like, you know, or participate in the sin. So can I sell,
however, to Michael this big pallet of לבונה, levonah, if Michael is
going to go now to the non-Jewish neighborhood and sell it to
them? So I am not transgressing the לפני עיוור lifnei iver of
their sin because I'm two degrees removed, but you know which לפני
עיוור lifnei iver I might be transgressing? Me? I'm transgressing making him
go over on לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. So the idea that a
double לפני, lifnei, two degrees removed, is not a problem is when
they're both non-Jews, okay? Because I'm not, because the non-Jew won't, the
non-Jew I'm interacting with won't transgress לפני עיוור lifnei iver because he's
not prohibited against לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, and the non-Jew who will
transgress, I'm not directly participating in his sin. But if it's a
selling it to a Jew who will then be over on לפני
עיוור lifnei iver by selling to a non-Jew, that could be a
different story. Okay, but anyway, that's a very important principle that your
לפני עיוור lifnei iver is only one degree removed, not two degrees
removed. Okay, ותרנגול לבן, vetarnigol lavan, a white, a white chicken.
Is a תרנגול tarnigol a chicken or a rooster? It's a rooster,
right? A תרנגולת tarnigolet is a chicken. So a rooster, a white
rooster, a white rooster. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי זירא אמר
רב זביד ואיכא דאמרי אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי זירא אמר רב
זירא, Amar Rabbi Yochanan Amar Rabbi Zeira Amar Rav Zvid ve'ika de'amri
Amar Rabbi Yochanan Amar Rabbi Zeira Amar Rav Zeira, תרנגול למי מותר
למכור
לו תרנגול לבן?
tarnigol lemi
mutar limkor lo tarnigol lavan? A guy who's going around and saying,
who has a rooster? I need a rooster! Any roosters, anyone? Then
you can sell him a white rooster, 'cause he's not particularly looking
for white roosters. תרנגול
לבנא מי? Tarnegol lavna mi? Guys going around saying, "Anybody got white
roosters?" So then אסור למכור לו תרנגול לבן. asur limkor lo tarnegol
lavan. You can't. All right, so that's pretty clear. Right, if the
person is generically looking for a rooster, it's okay. You don't have
to be concerned that the white rooster might be used for a
particular thing. It's only if he's specifically looking for a white rooster
is it a problem.
Now, let's see how that fits in our משנה Mishna because in
our משנה Mishna we have what seems to be some middle case.
תנן, Tnan, we taught in our משנה, Mishna, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer, מוכר הוא לו תרנגול לבן בין התרנגולים. mocher hu lo
tarnegol lavan bein hatarnegolim. You can sell him a white rooster amongst
other roosters. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דקאמר Ei
deka'amar תרנגול לבן למי, tarnegol lavan lemi, "Hey, who's got a white
rooster?" If תרנגול לבן למי, tarnegol lavan lemi, so then אפילו בין
התרנגולים נמי לא. afilu bein hatarnegolim nami lo. So why would רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allow you to sell him a white rooster mixed
up with other roosters? He's clearly looking for a white rooster. You
know, why does it all of a sudden become מותר muttar because
I say, "Well, I'll sell you the white rooster if you buy
two other black roosters with it"? Big deal, we know he's interested
in a white rooster. So that can't be the case that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים Chachamim are disagreeing with. אלא לאו,
Ela lav, it must be דקאמר deka'amar תרנגול למי, תרנגול למי. tarnegol
lemi, tarnegol lemi. He's going around saying, "Who has a rooster?" And
then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says in that case where he's generically
looking, you can sell it to him mixed, a white rooster mixed
up with other things. Okay. So, but then that, but and the
חכמים Chachamim would forbid even that. So even in that case, ואפילו
הכי רבי יהודה בין התרנגולים אין, בפני עצמו לא. v'afilu hachi Rabbi
Yehuda bein hatarnegolim in, bifnei atzmo lo. So even in the case
where he's generically looking, the most lenient position would be רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, who lets you sell it mixed up with the other
roosters. ולתנא קמא אפילו בין התרנגולים נמי לא. UleTanna Kamma afilu bein
hatarnegolim nami lo. But for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you couldn't
even sell it mixed up. So, so what's going on? The משנה
Mishna is clearly, you said two extremes: explicitly looking for a white
rooster is אסור, assur, generic is מותר. muttar. Okay, but our case
in the משנה Mishna can't be that he's explicitly looking. It must
be generic, and it seems that in the case of generic, there's
actually much more limited permission. Even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only allows
it in a very narrow circumstance. So where's your case that general
generic is okay for everybody? Then what's the case of the משנה?
Mishna? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק הכא
במאי עסקינן, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hacha bemai askinan, what are
we talking about? כגון דאמר זה וזה. kegon de'amar zeh v'zeh. The
case of the משנה Mishna is he said, "This and this." Now,
רש"י Rashi says what that means is somebody
is saying, "I need white, black, and red roosters. Anybody selling white,
black, and red roosters?" Okay, and in that case, that's where the
חכמים Chachamim say you can't sell him a white one because he
explicitly mentioned a white. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said you can
sell it to him with all the rest, because since he's asking
for a couple of different types, you can assume he's not specifically
interested for עבודה זרה avodah zarah purposes. תוספות, Tosafot, I'm going to
put רש"י Rashi aside. רש"י Rashi says it's exactly that he's sort
of mentioning different colors. תוספות Tosafot is a better explanation, I think,
especially as the גמרא Gemara continues.
And you are, always, not getting all colors? What?
And you are, whatever, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you are
giving him, or you're giving him a variety.
No, if he's asking for all colors then he's asking for nothing.
Right, so then that goes back to the generic case. Okay, תוספות
Tosafot is a better read I think both of the language of
the גמרא Gemara here and the way the גמרא Gemara continues. תוספות
Tosafot says no, no, no. It's not that he's saying, "I need
white, black, and red roosters." He goes, he goes to Michael here,
and Michael's got these roosters, and he's looking around and he says,
"I'll take that one and that one and that one." Okay, which
makes a lot of sense. And one of them is white. So
that's an interesting question. You know, and the other two aren't white.
So he, the fact that he's asking, yeah, he pointed to three,
and one of them is white and the other aren't. Oh, so
that's interesting. How do we look at that? Do we say the
white one he probably wants for עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? And maybe
he's even just saying the others as a way of letting the
Jew sell it to him. Or, or do we say that because
he's picking those out, he has no, he doesn't care about color,
he's just looking for the nice one? Right, so that's the debate.
And there the חכמים Chachamim say since he specifically pointed to the
white one, even though he pointed to others, you can't sell him
anything. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said no, you can sell it
to him with all of them together. We're going to assume that
he's not particularly interested in white. So that allows this statement now
to work. If he specifically says, "I'm looking for a white one,"
everybody says אסור. assur. If he just generically says, "Hey, I need
two roosters," and you want to pick out the white one and
sell him the white one, be my guest. But if he specifically
says, "This, this, and this," that's where they're debating. Can you sell
him the white one among the others? That's a great explanation. Okay.
Yes, is it assumed that אביי Abaye and the wholesaler, if you
are, or where that you're an accessory, is there any question, is
there any pushback to this אביי's Abaye's statement or the אביי Abaye
statement
that you can do two degrees removed? No, no, that's actually the
how we rule הלכה. halacha. But if the wholesaler is Jewish, then
that, that could be a problem. Right, right, yeah, yeah, that's the
way we rule. Okay. Now, גמרא Gemara says like this: כגון דאמר
זה
וזה. kegon de'amar zeh v'zeh. תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi similarly:
אמר רבי יהודה אימתי, Amar Rabbi Yehuda eimatai, when is it that
you're not allowed to sell him a white rooster? בזמן שאמר תרנגול
זה לבן, bizman she'amar tarnegol zeh lavan, if he comes up and
says, "That's the one I want," and the one he's pointing to
is a white one. אבל אם אמר זה וזה, Aval im amar
zeh v'zeh, this one and this one, and one of them is
a white one, מותר, muttar, then you can sell them both. Okay.
The חכמים Chachamim would say no. Great read of תוספות. Tosafot. ואפילו
אמר תרנגול זה עבודת כוכבים, V'afilu amar tarnegol zeh avodat kochavim, even
if he says, "I want this one," and it happens to be
a white one. If you know the particular context and you know
it's not an עבודה זרה Avoda Zara context, you're fine. Even if
he says "this one" and it happens to be white, but if
it's an עובד כוכבים שעשה משתה לבנו, oved kochavim she'asa mishta livno,
if you know that he's doing he has a big party that
day that he's making for his son, okay, או שהיה לו חולה
בתוך ביתו, o shehaya lo choleh betoch beito, or you see even
even the non-Jews knew about the magic of chicken soup, okay, except
they were making rooster soup. Anyway, or you know that he's sort
of buying this stuff because he's got a sick person and he's
trying to buy it for the food, מותר, mutar, and maybe I
don't know maybe they thought white roosters were special curative, you know,
properties, but that didn't make it עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. In that
case it's מותר. mutar. So if context is clear and, you know,
the context isn't explicit, the guy could have a sick son at
home or making a party and do be bringing a thing to
their god. Maybe דוקא davka they're bringing a thing to their god
to pray for their for their sick person. But so it's interesting
like how what's how much do you have to be certain X
or possible Y, you know, exactly how you assess it. But anyway,
but at least here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying is is
that there's a reasonable context that he's doing it for another purpose,
it's permissible. This is within רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda remember, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is more lenient in terms of what circumstances he thinks
it's okay to sell.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this, מותר. mutar. So גמרא
Gemara says really, is it מותר mutar if the guy's making a
party for his son? Party for his son presumably means when normally
when we say משתה לבנו, mishta livno, it means he's marrying off
his son. The גמרא Gemara saying one minute, when a guy marries
off his son, there's usually an עבודה זרה Avoda Zara ritual that
takes place, because that was actually one of the days they're not
allowed to do business with them. דתנן, De-tnan, עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
שעשה she'asa משתה mishta לבנו, livno, if he's making a, you know,
party for his son, אינו אסור אלא אותו היום ואותו איש בלבד.
eno assur ela oto hayom ve-oto ish bilvad.
You only can't do business with that person and on that day.
אותו היום ואותו איש Oto hayom ve-oto ish מי אסר? mi-assir? But
that person it's forbidden, there's some עבודה זרה Avoda Zara context there.
אמר רבי יצחק בר אבא משמיה דרבה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Abba
mishmi de-Rabbah, בתבזיג תנן. be-tavzig tnan. Okay, בתבזיג. be-tavzig.
We're talking about a תבזיג, tavzig, which רש''י Rashi says I don't
know what the heck that word means, but רש''י Rashi says basically
it means like some other party that's just for having fun and
it's not about we're not talking about a wedding. A picnic? Yeah,
fascinating. Okay, he's making a picnic. An informal meal. I got it.
I got it. It's not a wedding feast primarily.
Middle Iranian word picnic.
Middle Iranian word. Excellent. Okay. תנן, Tnan, ובשאר כל הדברים סתמם מותר
פירושם אסור. u-v'shear kol hadevarim stamam mutar perusham assur.
Now we're going to still go back and try to prove this
idea about when you're explicit it's always אסור, assur, when you're generic
it's always מותר, mutar, the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
חכמים Chachamim is when you say זה וזה. zeh va-zeh. Let's see
how that works with the rest of the משנה. Mishna. תנן, Tnan,
the משנה Mishna says, ובשאר כל הדברים סתמם מותר פירושם אסור. u-v'shear
kol hadevarim stamam mutar perusham assur.
All the other things that are not this white, you know, rooster
and the לבונה levonah and so on, if you're just generic it's
permissible, if you're explicit it's forbidden. מאי סתם ומאי פירוש? Mai stam
u-mai perush? What's generic and what's explicit? אילימא סתם דקאמר חטי חיוורתא.
Ileima stam de-ka-amar chitey chivrasa.
So now we're going to just use sort of parallel to the
white rooster, we're going to sort of imagine that it's something that's
not a rooster, it's I don't know wheat, white wheat. Okay, not
that they necessarily knew that people would use white wheat in a
ritual, it's just like wheat is now standing in for the place
of rooster. So white roosters we knew were used in this עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, you know, offering. Other things they're asking for something
bizarre so they're being specific but they're being specific without it being
clear about עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So if instead of saying white
rooster they said white wheat, okay, ופירוש, u-perush, so that would be
סתם stam that they were just saying something bizarre but not explicit
that it's עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, white wheat. ופירוש, U-perush, and being
explicit is דקאמר לעבודת כוכבים. de-ka-amar l'avodas kochavim. I need white wheat
for my עבודה זרה Avoda Zara ritual. So if that's true, that's
the case where the משנה Mishna saying if it's not the particular
items mentioned, then if they're just generic means generic meaning that they're
asking for weird stuff but not spelling out why it's okay. But
if they're explicit that they need it for their עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara ritual, it's no good. If that's what the משנה Mishna means
to draw the line between totally explicit and not, so why do
you need the משנה Mishna to teach me this? לא סתם צריכא
למימר דמזבנינן ולא פירוש צריכא למימר דלא מזבנינן. Lo stam tzricha lemeimar
de-mezabninan ve-lo perush tzricha lemeimar de-lo mezabninan.
It's obvious if the guy you don't have to tell me that
it's permissible to sell them white wheat, like why would I think
I couldn't sell them white wheat? It's bizarre but I don't know
any particular problematic context. And you wouldn't have to tell me that
I'm not allowed to sell it to them when they explicitly say
they're doing it for עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Both of those points
are obvious, okay. אלא Ella it must be that the line is
drawn elsewhere in the משנה. Mishna. סתם דקאמר חטי פירוש דקאמר חיוורתא.
Stam de-ka-amar chitey perush de-ka-amar chivrasa.
סתם Stam is that when they say wheat, you're allowed to sell
them סתם stam wheat, which okay obviously if they just say can
you sell me wheat that's obvious. But the חידוש chiddush is that
when they're explicit, meaning the question is what explicit means. Let's just
focus on that. If explicit means they explicitly say I need this
for my עבודה זרה Avoda Zara ritual, then of course you can't
sell it to them. So if the משנה Mishna is a חידוש,
chiddush, it means when they're explicit meaning when they're being highly particular
and asking for something bizarre but they're not explicit that it's for
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Okay, I need white wheat of this type
blah blah blah. Okay, so in that type of a case then
we're going to say ah it's so bizarre they probably need it
for עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Maybe that's the case what the משנה
mishnah is saying. If that's true we see, says the גמרא, gemara,
so מכלל, miklal, so if that's true that the case when it's
not a rooster
being particular and being forbidden does not mean saying explicitly עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. It means being particular in the sense of, you know,
being very specific.
Okay, מכלל, miklal, from that we can infer דתרנגול detarnigol that when
it comes to the rooster, אפילו סתמא נמי לא, afilu stama nami
lo, that even if they are not specific, even if they just
generically ask for a rooster, you can't sell them a white one.
Okay? So do you got that? It's a little confusing but
basically keep on losing my whatever.
When in doubt use your hand. Okay, so anyway you have the
idea like this: you have
rooster,
that's one case, who's selling a rooster, right? And then who's selling
a white rooster, right? Those are the two cases and we said
that this is always מותר, mutar, this is always אסור, assur, and
the middle case was like a זה וזה zeh v'zeh type of
a case. Okay, but fine, that's the middle case. But anyway, but
the initial statement was this is always מותר mutar and this is
always אסור. assur. All right? But now the משנה mishnah says when
you're not dealing with a rooster, okay, then סתמן staman is מותר
mutar and פירושן peirushan is אסור. assur. All right?
So if פירושן peirushan is אסור assur by a not-rooster, when you're
dealing with wheat, okay, you have three cases: wheat,
white wheat,
and right, white wheat for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. White wheat for
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So it says, so which explicit case here,
this is obviously not explicit, which explicit case here is forbidden? It
says if when the משנה mishnah says explicit is forbidden it means
this and that's patently obvious, that can't be. So when it says
explicit is forbidden it must mean something like specific but not really
really explicit. That's
forbidden by the wheat. Then the case that's forbidden by the rooster
must just be the סתם stam rooster. And even if somebody is
just generically looking for a rooster you can't sell them a white
rooster because the משנה mishnah says roosters are particularly problematic, white roosters
are particularly, everything else is only a problem when it's explicit. Meaning
the way to say it, everything else has to be explicit. So
if everything else has to be explicit and that means this, then
the rooster case doesn't have to be explicit, even if the person's
just generically asking for a rooster, it should be forbidden to sell
them a white rooster. So that shows against the idea that a
generic rooster is okay. So the גמרא gemara says, אמר ליה לעולם
דסתמא דקאמר חיטי
חיורתא. amar lei l'olam d'stama d'ka'amar chitti chivarta.
No, no, no. When סתם, stam, not explicit, means he's just saying
white wheat. פירושן דקאמר לעבודה זרה, peirushan d'ka'amar l'avodah zarah,
and when it's explicit by things other than a rooster it means
he's really explicitly saying for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ופירושן איצטריכא ליה,
v'peirushan itztericha lei, but yes there is a חידוש. chiddush. What's the
חידוש? chiddush?
Obviously if he says I'm using this for עבודה זרה avodah zarah
obviously it's אסור. assur. So no, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka datach amina,
I might have thought האי גברא לאו לעבודה זרה קא בעי. hai
gavra lav l'avodah zarah ka ba'ei. He really maybe you can even
sell him white wheat even though he says for עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. Why? Because maybe he doesn't really need it for עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah.
So if he doesn't need it for עבודה זרה avodah zarah why
is he saying that? So אלא מיבזח הוא דקא בזיח בעבודה זרה.
ella mivzach hu d'ka vazich b'avodah zarah.
This guy is like משוגע meshugga after his עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
וסבר v'savar he's really cleaved to his עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. כי
היכי דהוא גברא אביק בה, ki heichi d'hu gavra avik bah, and
this person thinks this is such a brilliant psychological read, right? Do
you think that because you have this obsession and you're crazy about
something, like think about somebody I don't know like, you know, like
kids are like totally obsessed about like, you know, D&D or whatever,
you know, people have got these obsessions, so they assume everybody always
wants to talk about it, right? So you think that because you're
crazy cleaving to this, actually I shouldn't say that about my kids,
that's לשון הרע, lashon hara, they only talk about their friends who
are crazy about it. Okay. But anyway, but you know, somebody has
an obsession, they always want to, they assume everybody's interested in their
obsession, okay? כי היכי דהוא גברא אביק בה, ki heichi d'hu gavra
avik bah, he thinks the same way he is like so cleaving
to it כולי עלמא נמי אביקי, kuli alma nami aviki, everybody else
is crazy about his עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ואימא הכי, v'eima hachi,
so he figures I'll tell the storekeeper I'm going to be using
this for my עבודה זרה avodah zarah ritual, he'll probably give me
a discount because everybody loves, you know, Zeus, everybody's crazy about Zeus.
So he says ואימא הכי כי היכי דלוזיל ליה, v'eima hachi ki
heichi d'lozeil lei, they'll give it to me at a discount. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that we don't attribute it to that.
If the guy explicitly says עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it's עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So anyway what we're saying is is that this is
permissible to even sell them a white rooster if he's generically asking,
this is forbidden. In something that's not a rooster, even this is
permissible even if he's specific. It's only a problem if he explicitly
labels and he tells you black and white he's going to use
it for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, but anyway that's the basic,
that's the basic division, that certain things you know are being used
for עבודה זרה avodah zarah purposes. What does know? Is it a
hundred percent? But anyway, but certain things that you know when they
specifically identify the type of thing that you know like they say
white rooster, that is a problem.
danger here that you know, you know, the non-idolater sees you selling
it to a Jew and then he says you sold it to
him, you won't sell it to me in anger and, you know.
Oh, that's I mean yes, that's a good point. The ראשונים Rishonim
definitely deal with concerns about איבה eivah and other types of things,
that if there's no good way of getting out of it then
you have to, you know, then yes, those were factors that definitely
played in in the Middle Ages, a hundred percent. I actually in
a minute want to read תוספות Tosafot because תוספות Tosafot is going
to connect this to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi trade in church ritual objects,
we'll see in a minute. Yes.
I feel like there's a case that would be a good like
case study for it, which is like you have five roosters and
the white rooster's like the white rooster is the worst of the
bunch like
it's sick, it's not,
and he's like, yeah, I want it for like you know chicken
soup and you're like, that doesn't make any sense. Right,
how much do you use other contextual clues? Like even if something
otherwise wouldn't be a problem because of this structure that we set
out, but there's things that are sort of the reverse. As opposed
to signaling you the same way when he says a white rooster,
like this one or whatever it is, but you really have reason
to think, you know, good reason to think he's not using it
for עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, let's say it's the flip, it doesn't
technically it should be okay but there's reason to think to be
suspicious in the other way. Yeah, look, that's the general issue we're
going to be dealing with here for a couple of for a
while in terms of, I mean actually we leave this and then
we come back to it. There's
like לפני עור Lifnei iver is a recurring theme in trying to
figure out exactly what the parameters are. So we'll we'll be revisiting
it. Okay, let's do a little bit I want to get further
and I want to see a תוספות. Tosafot. So it says like
this, it says, okay,
and talking about this, actually Jenna this is similar to your case
except it's like in the opposite to make it permissible. Jenna was
asking using context clues to make it forbidden. Let's take a look.
בעי רב אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, תרנגול
לבן קטוע לי, Tarnigol lavan katu'a li, I need a white rooster
with a broken leg, okay, so which is bizarre. First of all
who דוקא davka wants something with a broken leg? Maybe he's saying
I'm looking for a damaged type to try to get a twenty
percent discount. But remember, a broken leg means that or a chopped
off finger means that they won't use it for עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. Okay, so in then and you don't have one with a
broken finger, with a chopped off finger, but you do have a
whole white rooster. Can you sell it to him? Can you say
since he was only asking for one with a with a chopped
off finger presumably he doesn't use it for עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
or maybe he's a little too smart for me? Maybe he realizes
it's easier to get a whole white rooster than a broken white
rooster and he was exactly hoping for this scenario. Okay, so תרנגול
לבן קטוע לי מהו למכור לו תרנגול
לבן
שלם,
Tarnigol lavan katu'a
li mahu limkor lo tarnigol lavan shalem, can you sell him a
whole white rooster? מי אמרינן מכדי אמר קטוע לעבודה זרה לא קבעי
ליה, Mi amrina mikdi amar katu'a le-avodah zarah lo kaba'ei lei, since
he's saying I want one with a chopped off finger, so he's
not using it for עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, או דלמא ערומי הוא
דקאערים, o dilma arumay hu de-ka-arim, or maybe he's just being scheming,
you know, and he figures out okay it's much more I'll say
this they'll think I don't need it for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
and and they'll probably offer me a whole one. So אם תמצא
לומר ערומי הוא דקאערים, Im timtze lomar arumay hu de-ka-arim, if you
say no that case clearly he we have to be concerned that
he's scheming. Okay, in that case let's say he says תרנגול לבן
למי תרנגול לבן למי, Tarnigol lavan le-mi tarnigol lavan le-mi, he goes
around saying I need a white rooster. ויהבו ליה שחור ושקל, ve-yahavu
lei shahor ve-shakal, and they say the guy says to him I
don't have any white roosters I got a black one. He says
that's fine and he buys that. And then he keeps on going,
anybody else? Okay, ואדו ושקלו, ve-adu ve-shaklo, and they give him a
red one and he takes it. ויהבו ליה אדו ושקלו, ve-yahavu lei
adu ve-shaklo, מהו למכור לו לבן, mahu limkor lo lavan, and then
he's still looking, can you then be the one to sell him
the white one? מי אמרינן כיון דיהבי שחור ושקל אדו ושקל לא
לעבודה זרה קבעי, Mi amrina keivan de-yahavi shahor ve-shakal adu ve-shakal lo
le-avodah zarah kaba'ei, since he's taking red and black or whatever he
might want white because it looks nice, you know he might want
right but he's not specifically focused he's happy to take other ones
as well he still wants a white one though. So do we
say that that is enough of an indication he's not looking at
it for עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? או דלמא ערומי הוא דקאערים, o
dilma arumay hu de-ka-arim, or even here he's got he figures out
I'll keep on buying the roosters until somebody finally sells me a
white one. כמא דקאערים? kema de-ka-arim? תיקו, Teiku, so we don't know.
So we don't know in that case is that enough of a
signal that even though he's asking for white he doesn't really need
it for עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So right so he has cases
where it would be problematic we use possible context clues to say
it's not for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and Jenna wants to argue
we should also be מחמיר machmir in the opposite direction when it's
appropriate and the answer is probably correct. Let's finish the משנה mishnah
and then I want to read a תוספות. Tosafot. רבי מאיר אומר
אף דקל טוב, Rabbi Meir omer af dekel tav, Rabbi Meir says
we can't even sell them this דקל טוב, dekel tav, this good
palm tree. אמר ליה רב חסדא לאבימי, Amar lei Rav Hisda le-Avimi,
Rav Hisda said to Avimi, גמירי, gmiri, we have a tradition דעבודה
זרה דאברהם אבינו ארבע מאה פירקי הוי. de-avodah zarah de-Avraham Avinu arba
me'ah pirkai hava. Avraham Avinu had a מסכת עבודה זרה masechet Avodah
Zarah and it had four hundred chapters in it. Okay? It was
a really big מסכת masechet of גמרא, Gemara, took them a whole
year to get through it even doing the דף יומי. Daf Yomi.
So anyway, and that he did a chapter a year. Anyway, the
point of saying that four hundred chapters obviously four hundred is like
saying a thousand, a million, it's like saying that there was so
much idolatry in Avraham Avinu's day that he needed like if if
he would have had a tractate of עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, it
would have had to have had hundreds of chapters in it, okay?
To deal with all of the details of all of the idolatry.
Okay.
Okay. ואנן חמישה תנן, Veanan chamisha tnan, we have a mere five
chapters in our tractate ולא ידעינן מאי קאמרינן velo yadainan mai kaamrinan
and we don't even understand the reality of what it's describing, okay?
We're so, you know, we're so oblivious to the real details of
the practices that are surrounding us. So ומאי קשיא umai kashya what
is it that he's sort of making this, you know, sort of
a statement about? What is he getting, what is he getting exasperated
about or frustrated about? ומאי קשיא דתנן רבי מאיר אומר אף דקל
טב חצב ונקלס אסור למכור לעובדי כוכבים. umai kashya detnan Rabbi Meir
omer af dekel tav chatzav veniklas assur limkor leovdei kochavim. You can't
sell them these things. דקל טב, dekel tav, חצב chatzav and ננקלס.
niklas. So דקל טב ודלא מזדבני מזבנינן? dekel tav udela mizdavni mizvninan?
He says I don't understand this. What, you can't sell them a
good palm tree? האי דקל ביש מזבנינן? hai dekel bish mizvninan? You
can sell them a bad palm tree? והתנן אין מוכרים להם במחובר
לקרקע? vehatnan ein mochrom lahem bemochubar lekarka? But we taught that you
can't sell them anything attached to the ground and that has to
do with, like as we said, the has less to do with
sort of pagan ritual and that had to do with the fact
that like, you know, giving them more of a presence in the
land of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So that's specifically about land in
the land of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So anyway, so it's funny
because you would expect and that's going to come up in this
like two lines in the גמרא Gemara that it's a frustration of
we don't really understand the specifics of the pagan rituals, we don't
understand why specifically these items, what they were used for. That's what
he was saying. Here it's the normal question. What does it have
to do with אברהם אבינו's Avraham Avinu מסכת עבודה זרה? Maseches Avoda
Zara? It's like I don't get why this is a pro- why
only this is a problem, it should be that all things that
are attached to the ground are a problem. Like, okay, I mean
I hear the question, but like what does it have to do
with comparing it to אברהם אבינו, Avraham Avinu, you know? Anyway, אמר
ליה amar lei
no, מאי דקל טב פירות דקל טב. mai dekel tav peiros dekel
tav. It doesn't mean you can't actually sell a palm tree, it
means you can't sell the fruit of a palm tree. Now does
good is good here a descriptor, a good palm tree or many
ראשונים Rishonim assume it means like it's a type of a species
of palm tree. You can't sell the fruit from a particular species
of palm tree. So maybe that's his point, if we understood the
pagan practices better I would have immediately understood that that was the
context. That when it says don't sell them a דקל טב dekel
tav it didn't mean the palm tree itself, it meant don't sell
them the fruit of this particular type of a palm tree. וכן
אמר רב הונא פירות דקל טב. Vechen amar Rav Huna peiros dekel
tav. Fine. חצב, Chatzav, now what's חצב? chatzav? כספא. Kispa. That's כספא.
kispa. Whatever that is. רשי Rashi says it's maybe some type of
a grass.
נקלס Niklas what's נקלס? niklas? St. Niklas, there you go. כי יתיב
אתיני אמר רב יהודה אמר רב יוסף קורייטי. Ki yasiv asini amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav Yosef kuraiti. It's קורייטי. kuraiti. Again exactly what
this is, some say it's like some type of a of a
of a date or something. Anyway, אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי. amar
lei Abaye leRav Dimi.
Okay let's first finish then you'll read the note. אמר ליה אביי
לרב דימי תנן נקלס ולא ידעינן מהו. amar lei Abaye leRav Dimi
tnan niklas velo yadainan mahu. The משנה Mishna says נקלס niklas and
I don't know what it is. ואמרת קורייטי veamrat kuraiti and you
said to me oh it's קורייטי. kuraiti. What does the good of
that give me? ולא ידעינן מאי אהנית לן. velo yadainan mai ahanis
lan. I don't know how you're helping me. You translated one word
I don't know into another word I don't know. שקויח, Shkoiyach, what
good does that do me? So that's how I feel sometimes and
the גמרא Gemara is trying to tell us what certain things mean.
So אמר ליה amar lei no, אהניי ahanai I help you דכי
אזלת התם dechi azlas hasam when you go there like ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael אמרת להו נקלס amras lehu niklas and you tell the
people hey what's נקלס niklas ולא ידעי velo yadai and they don't
know ואמרת להו veamras lehu then you can say קורייטי kuraiti how
about קורייטי? kuraiti? Do you know what קורייטי kuraiti is? וידעי veyadai
they say oh קורייטי kuraiti I know that ומחו לך umachavu lach
and then they'll show it to you. So if I gave you
another word it might help you identify it, now you have two
words that you can use to ask around and to identify it.
Okay what does the what do your footnotes what do your notes
say there?
It says a type of food superior species of date who is
named after philosopher Niklas.
Oh it is Niklas?
Yeah. Who used to send these dates from Syria to Augustus Caesar
in Rome.
Okay there you go. Niklas dates.
There is another reading by the way of the רמבם Rambam maybe
have ניקליבון Niklavon instead of.
Okay. Alright very good. Anyway so the basic פשט pshat of this
is don't sell them things that they are explicitly labeling for עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara but things that you know are classically used for
that purpose you know and they are you know and they're specifically
identifying that they don't say for עבודה זרה Avoda Zara but the
type of thing that you know is specifically like who sells me
you know they specifically they're specific about what they want and that
type of thing is generally used for עבודה זרה Avoda Zara right
the white rooster example like that's a problem. So take a look
at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says like this. תוספות Tosafos in the
middle of this תוספות חצב Tosafos Chatzav big תוספות Tosafos talking about
what type of grass it is or whatever. Anyway if you look
in the middle he says the line starts with שמעתא shmaita כתב
רבינו ברוך kasav Rabbeinu Baruch
it's like you see where there's an asterisk in the גמרא Gemara
and says דעבודת כוכבים דאברהם אבינו da'avodas kochavim deAvraham Avinu the line
starts with the asterisk. So if you go directly across to the
תוספות Tosafos he says the following: כתב רב ברוך ברבי Kasav Rav
Baruch beribbi כיון דשאר דברים פירושן אסור keivan deshaar devarim peirushan assur
since other things that they are explicit they're forbidden I would actually
say since things that you know are being used are forbidden even
if it's not explicit anyway אם כן אסור לאדם למכור לכומר עובד
כוכבים im kein assur leadam limkor lechomer oved kochavim
you cannot sell to a priest idolater. priest of עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, meaning a priest, a Christian priest,
לבונה, levonah, frankincense, דהוי כמו פירושן, de-havei kemo perushan, that's like being
explicit to adore. I don't know why he has to say that
since the משנה Mishnah mentions incense, right? Yeah, I don't know why
he has to go like לבונה levonah is like it's מפורש. mefurash.
לבונה levonah is one of those things in the משנה Mishnah anyway,
but maybe you would think that our, you know, the rituals nowadays
are different than the rituals then. But either way, it's clear what
they're going to use the incense for. Okay, דהוי כמו פירושן, de-havei
kemo perushan, it's like being explicit. דדבר ברור הוא דלקרובת בעי ליה,
de-davar barur hu de-likrovas ba-ei lei, it's obviously that they're going to
use it for some type of an offering, burning incense. ועובר משום
לפני עור, ve-over mishum lifnei iver, you transgress לפני עור. lifnei iver.
וגם אסור למכור שעוה לשום עובד כוכבים. ve-gam assur limkor sha'avah leshum
oved kochavim. Not
that's to the priests. You know, maybe other people they burn this,
the incense in their homes just to smell nice, okay, but for
the priests, you know what the context. Or maybe that's why he
had to say it's כמו, kemo, it's explicit, because a normal person
you can sell incense because people burn incense in their homes just
to smell nice, but a priest creates a context in which you
know that it's clear that they're buying the incense for this ritual.
Okay, and when the context is clear, it is forbidden. And he
says it should also therefore be forbidden to sell to anyone, you
know, שעוה, sha'avah,
wax. Because what do they use wax for? Oh, not in general,
but ביום איד. be-yom eid. You can't sell them wax on their
holidays because then they make these wax candles and they burn it
before, you know, the icons, okay, and before the statues. ביום איד
ההוא, be-yom eid ha-hu,
that, that holiday. This must be a, anyway, אבל ודאי בשאר ימים,
aval vadai be-sha'ar yamim, other days, מותר, mutar, it would be permissible.
But in days where you know what they're going to be using
it for, it should be forbidden. וכן אותם כלי עבודת כוכבים שישראל
קונה לאחר שפגמו עובד כוכבים וביטלו. ve-chein otam klei avodat kochavim she-Yisrael
koneh le-achar she-pigmo oved kochavim u-bitlo.
Let's say you have some type of a vessel that was used
by one Christian that was used in some type of a worship,
but then they, you know, damaged it and it's a way of
saying like I'm no longer using this for a ritual purpose. And
what you're going to do is you're going to buy it from
him and then resell it to another, another Christian, you know, and
they will be happy to use it for, for that, but like
a chalice or something like that. מכל מקום אסור
למכור לעובד כוכבים כמו שהוא, mi-kol makom assur limkor le-oved kochavim kemo
she-hu, עד שינתח כולו, ad she-yinatei-ach kulo, until you actually melt it
down. ובשביל פגימה אחת אינו מניח להטיב יין לקלס עבודת כוכבים. u-vishvil
pgimah achat eino mani-ach le-hativ yayin le-khales avodas kochavim.
Just because of a certain type of a dent, they're still going
to, that won't stop them from using it as a type of
a chalice which they'll use in their, you know, in their ritual.
והכי נמי ספרים פסולים. ve-hachi nami sefarim pesulim. Now here what becomes
interesting is that these types of things, are these actual objects that
are being, you know, obviously he's assuming Christianity is עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. But are these objects of actual offerings? Like you can say
incense is an offering, you can say burning candles, right? Is, doesn't
the word votive mean an offering? Votive,
doesn't the word votive mean like a קרבן? korban? No? I think
so.
Oh, they have votive candles.
I understand because those are talking about wax. So that's what I'm
saying. Like some of these I think are types of, can be
understood as types of offerings. But, but now he's getting to, now
what but when you use a, like a votary. A person such
as a monk or nun who has made vows or dedication of
religious service. So it's not an offering. Okay, it's like a vow.
Anyway, but now we're getting to using like a chalice. Is a
chalice a, it's a כלי kli that is used, is that considered
that the, well I guess if you're using it in the, what
do you call it? In the, what is that that they do?
In the, what's the wafer and the wine, what's it called?
Come on people, where's your knowledge of Christianity?
It's when they, when the body,
anyway, transubstantiation, whatever it is. Anyway, no, somebody, anyway. So is that
a type of an offering? I mean that's in a way even
like more challenging. It's not an offering to, it's a, it's a
transferring the physical object into the body and the, sacrament. No, sacrament
is generic. Sacrament, like a lot of things are the sacrament. What's
that specific sacrament? Anyway, the Eucharist.
The Eucharist, thank you. Anyway, that is turning, like, so, so that's
presumably all of those things. Right? So it's interesting. Like that's the
question I was raising before. How much is it just that it's
used in a ritual, and how much does it have to be
seen as a direct, you know, act of an offering to or
a direct type of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? This is treating Christianity
as עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? So he's, he has, he has
the incense, the candles, the chalice used for the wine. But then
he says, והכי נמי ספרים פסולים, ve-hachi nami sefarim pesulim, הראוים לתפלה
בבית עבודת כוכבים. ha-reuyim le-tefillah be-veit avodat kochavim.
Now
the word, first of all, what they, a classic thing that the
גמרא Gemara does and the ראשונים Rishonim follow is it changes generic
or positive words when dealing with עבודה זרה avodah zarah to derogatory
words. It's the opposite of a euphemism. It's called I think a
dysphemism. Fancy word, try to use that in Scrabble. Anyway, so when
they refer to their house of prayer, instead of calling it בית
תפלה, beit tefillah, they call it בית תפלה. beit tiflah. תפלה tiflah
is like nonsense. Okay, but anyway. So he says selling them books,
now presumably books means like... I think it sort of means like
Bibles, okay, selling them Bibles that you have or, you know, because
they'll use like I don't know a תהלים Tehillim or something like
that. So and they're going to use it now in their church.
So אסור למכור להם asur limkor lahem you can't sell them לכומרים
lekumrim to-oh now maybe you can sell it to a Christian who's
just going to use it at home for study, but can you
use it in something that's going to be used in their church?
דאזלינן משום לפני עור. De'azlinan mishum lifnei iver. דאפילו עובד כוכבים שאינו
כומר אסור. De'afilu oved kochavim she'eino komer asur. דבוודאי יהננו או ימכרנו
לכומר. Devavaday yehenenu o yimkerenu lekomer. You can't even sell it to
a Christian who's not a priest because he'll just give it to
the church. So now using something as a, you know, as something
that they're going to read from, they're going to chant from in
the church, they'll read the Psalms, they'll read a passage of the
Bible, right? All of these things sound like the תוספות Tosafos are
saying these are not just rituals. These are all things that are
done in church. These are acts of worship. These are acts of
and if we consider Christianity עבודה זרה, avoda zara, these are all
acts of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay, so א', alef, this shows
us this is very stark in terms of clearly how much it's
like using this as like things that are straight עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. And then saying you can't sell any of these types of
things, right, that you know they're going to use it. So the
question is how did the ראשונים Rishonim do trade in objects of
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So in objects of excuse me, in Christian
objects of worship. So two basic answers developed. One was יה-, ya,
put this תוספות Tosafos aside, developed the next stage where we said
Christianity is not עבודה זרה avoda zara for Christians. So it's not
you know it's not עבודה זרה avoda zara for non-Jews. It's only
a problem for Jews. So therefore even though for me it would
be completely עבודה זרה, avoda zara, I'm not aiding and abetting them
in their forbidden worship because for them it is not עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. That's one answer. That's clearly not what this תוספות Tosafos
is saying. Another answer emerges from the next משנה. mishnah. So let's
read the next משנה. mishnah. מקום שנהגו למכור בהמה דקה לעובדי כוכבים
מוכרין.
Makom
shenahagu
limkor behema daka le'ovdei kochavim mochrin.
Where they had a practice to sell small animals like sheep and
goats to non-Jews you could sell it. מקום שנהגו שלא למכור אין
מוכרין. Makom shenahagu shelo limkor ein mochrin. Where there was not the
practice you could not sell it. Okay ובכל מקום, uvchol makom, but
in any place whatever the practice was, אין מוכרין להם בהמה גסה.
ein mochrin lahem behema gassa. You don't sell them large animals like
cows and horses עגלים וסייחים agalim vesayachim
or even like calves and foals שלמים ושבורים shlemim ushvurim
whether they're young or old you know even if they're young and
even whether they're whole or even if they're broken you know you
can't sell them. רבי יהודה מתיר בשבורה. Rabbi Yehuda matir bishvura. Rabbi
Yehuda allows with a with an animal like a broken leg. ובן
בתירא מתיר בסוס. Uven Beteira matir besus. Ben Beteira allows a horse.
Now what is the problem here? The problem here is well different
ones. The גמרא Gemara is going to say the problem with selling
small animals is do we suspect them of doing acts of bestiality.
So when you sell them a small animal an animal they'll maybe
do an act of bestiality with it. Fine. That's the small animals.
What's the problem with the big animal? That's where there's a debate
whether we're concerned about that. What's the big animals? So the גמרא
Gemara is going to say the big animals is a concern that
you won't actually sell it to them you'll if we let you
sell it you'll come to lend it to them or rent it
to them and if you're renting it to them and they'll use
it on שבת Shabbos then you'll transgress the prohibition of having your
animal do work on שבת. Shabbos. Now I have to tell you
we'll get to all of that, but I have and then that's
the question about does that apply to a horse? Does that apply
to something with a broken leg that can't really do work on
שבת? Shabbos? It frames it all as a שבת Shabbos issue. I
personally think that the original meaning of this was different. The original
meaning of this was likely we saw before about like why you're
supposed to be trying to buy animals from them in the marketplace.
That it's an issue about the Jewish presence in the land of
Israel. So they did not want you selling to this was specifically
a land of Israel concern not Jew and non-Jew whatever. They did
not want you selling these things that established somebody's presence like as
you know the agricultural presence, the rootedness in the land. So the
small sheep you know the whatever you know the types of sheep
or whatever they go grazing that's a nomadic type of a thing
that's not as big of an issue, right, but like the horse-
the cows you know that's like the cows are there you know
they're stable you use them for plowing you know that's more of
a sense of a presence in the land and there's some maybe
debate about the horses or whatever. So I think and we'll see
this later, תוספות Tosafos we already mentioned the issue a minute ago
in the גמרא Gemara about selling them actual real estate, right? Oh
what do you mean a תר- tar- you're not allowed to sell
them any land etc. So I see this as specifically about the
land of Israel and presence in the land which connects with other
things but the גמרא Gemara at least interprets this as a concern
of either שבת Shabbos concerns at the end or bestiality concerns in
the beginning. So let's just read that first line in the beginning
and then I want to show you one line in תוספות. Tosafos.
למימר Lemaimar says the גמרא Gemara דאיסורא ליכא de'issura leika there's no
prohibition by selling them these small animals. מנהגא איכא minhaga eika it's
a question of a מנהג minhag דאיכא היכא דנהוג איסורא נהוג de'eika
heicha denahug issura nahug where there a
practice a custom to have this prohibition of selling small animals it's
in place. היכא דנהוג היתרא נהוג Heicha denahug hetera nahug where it's
permissible where it's permissible it's permissible. ורמינהו Ureminhu and I ask them
back. אין מעמידין בהמה בפונדקאות של עובדי כוכבים. Ein ma'amidin behema bepundekaos
shel ovdei kochavim. You can't leave your animal in a like a
like a stable you know you're going into the inn don't leave
your animal in the stable of the non-Jews. מפני שחשודים על הרביעה
Mipnei shechashudim al harevia
because they're suspect of doing acts of bestiality and you don't want
to expose you know your animal to them to acts of bestiality
as לפני עור lifnei iver you don't want it done to your
animal. So אמר רב אמר. Amar Rav Amar. So although, so that
seems like it should always be אסור. assur. So אמר רבא, amar
Rava, מקום שהתירו למכור התירו ליחד, mokom shehitiru limkor hitiru leyached, מקום
שאסרו ליחד אסרו למכור. mokom sheasru leyached asru limkor.
No, they are connected. Where it says you're not allowed to leave
a non-Jew alone with your animal, those are in the places where
they don't sell small animals to non-Jews. That's where they suspect non-Jews
of these types of acts. And the places where they do sell
small animals to non-Jews, they don't suspect non-Jews of these types of
acts and you're allowed to leave your animals with the non-Jews. It's
all connected. Some places yes, some places no. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbi
Eliezer omer, now רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says, אף מקום שאסרו ליחד
מותר למכור. af mokom sheasru leyached mutar limkor. No, no.
There's a difference between selling and leaving your animal alone with a
non-Jew. Maybe you can never leave your animal alone with a non-Jew.
We suspect them of these things. By the way, this is pretty
horrific, you gotta admit, right? To like this becomes the issue, which
I'll get back to. What is the lens that we look at
the outside world through? So until now it's been okay, they don't
do תורה ומצוות, Torah u'mitzvot, they do עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Fine,
we all know they do עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now it's like
you leave them alone with your animal, they're going to do an
act of bestiality. Right? I mean, like, you know, that completely, like,
you know, obviously is an act of othering, significant.
And he sees us drinking blood.
And we see them as doing acts of bestiality. Right. רבי אליעזר
אומר אף מקום שאסרו ליחד מותר למכור. Rebbi Eliezer omer af mokom
sheasru leyached mutar limkor. מאי טעמא? mai taama? עובד כוכבים חס על
בהמתו שלא תעקר. akum chas al behemto shelo teaker. No,
if you sell, you can sell it because he won't do it
to his own animal because he's afraid this act will make his
animal, you know, sterile. So he'll do it to your animal; he
won't do it to his animal. So you could be allowed to
sell it. Maybe you can sell, there are different practices about selling,
but it's always forbidden to leave him alone because it's with your
animal. All right. So we'll get back to this tomorrow about this
way of looking at these non-Jews as all ready to do these
acts of bestiality. Right now I just want to focus on one
thing, which is why should it be forbidden to sell what? It's
a לפני עיוור? lifnei iver? But how about the fact that he
must have his own animals he could do it with anyway? Like,
he doesn't need you. I'm sure he's got his own animals. Why
is it לפני עיוור? lifnei iver? Okay. So you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, very important תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot מקום שנהגו שלא למכור אין
מוכרין. mokom shenahagu shelo limkor ein mocherin. תוספות Tosafot says, פירוש משום
חשש רביעה peirush mishum chashash revia because of this concern of bestiality.
ואמרה אל לפני עיוור, v'amra al lifnei iver, you'll be transgressing לפני
עיוור. lifnei iver. ומדלא מצחיק הכא בין אית ליה בהמה ובין לית
ליה בהמה. umide lo matzkach hacha bein it lei behema uvein leit
lei behema.
Why doesn't it distinguish between whether he's got such an animal himself
or not? אלמא משמע דאפילו אית ליה לעובד כוכבים בהמה אחריניתא אסור.
alma mashma dafilu it lei l'akum behema achrinita assur. Even if he
has an animal אחריניתא, achrinita, אסור. assur. It's a לפני עיוור lifnei
iver problem. Okay. So, so that's the question. Is it לפני עיוור?
lifnei iver? And then he says well but it's קשיא, kashya, later
we
it sounds like earlier, לרבנו חננאל, leRabbenu Chananel, מאי שנא דהכא גבי
תקרובת דאית ליה דהוה בהמה שרי וליש משום לפני עיוור? mai shena
dehacha gabi tikrovet deit lei d'hava behema shari v'leish mishum lifnei iver?
וסמכינן להא דלפני דפירש? v'samchina l'ha d'lifne d'perish? But he says I
don't get it. Before it sounded like if the non-Jews already have
an object and they can do the עבירה aveira anyway with the
object they have, you don't transgress. So why are you transgressing לפני
עיוור lifnei iver if they have their own animal? ותירץ רב יהודה
דשאני רביעה דמיתאוה לכל בהמה ובהמה. v'tirutz d'Rav Yehuda d'shani revia shemitaveh
lechol behema va'behema. Okay.
So he basically says
that no, you know, whatever, no accounting for people's sexual desire. So
maybe he's got his own animal, but it's something about your animal
that he's particularly lusting for. Anyway, the reason I read this תוספות,
Tosafot, I'm sure this
is taking time for you to absorb this lovely discussion, but anyway,
the reason I just want to say the following point, the reason
I'm reading this תוספות Tosafot is this question of if he has
it anyway, do I transgress לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, did become an
important basis for allowing them to do business with Christian ritual objects.
Why? Here I now, here I am, I'm selling this guy a
chalice, candles, whatever I'm selling, frankincense. So if you say I don't
transgress לפני עיוור lifnei iver if he already has it, okay, if
he already has it I can sell it to him. Of course,
how does that help me? Let's say he doesn't have it. Okay,
ah, what if he doesn't have it but he could easily buy
it? Let's say there's other people that are selling it to him,
right? He can just go to the store and buy frankincense. There's
a whole frankincense market. I'm one of ten frankincense sellers. So if
you say you don't transgress לפני עיוור lifnei iver when he has
it already, it's not a big jump to say that you don't
transgress לפני עיוור lifnei iver if he can easily access it without
your help. You got that? So therefore, if I can, therefore, that
becomes a היתר heter that I can sell these ritual objects if
other people are selling it as well and therefore he doesn't need
me. Of course the irony becomes, let's say all the other people
selling it as well are all Jewish. We are the four people,
the four of us in this room have the entire market of
frankincense for the Christians, okay? And we can all do it by
the justification that if he's not going to buy it from me,
he'll buy it from you.
But we all decide to do it at the same time, none
of us is עובר על לפני עיוור. over al lifnei iver. It
becomes a little ironic. Okay. But that does become the other basis
in which they were allowed, they permitted this type of a trade,
yeah.